This is a work of fiction.
Any resemblance to real persons, groups or events is purely coincidental.
Let's imagine that one day I took the PA system's mic and said, "What a nice day".
ある日俺がマイクを持ち本日は晴天なりといったとする
Some who heard me might think:
それを聞いた者はこう思うだろう
"Oreki wanted to test the mic".
「折木君はマイクのテストがしたいのだな」と
Modern Japanese            quiz
Ten seconds left!
後十秒
But others might think, instead:
しかし別の者はこう思うかもしれない
Five, four, three, two, one,
五　四　三　二　一
Which is the correct meaning of the word "analogy"?
a, A similarity that may be used as a basis for comparison
b, A direct analysis of the differences between two objects
"He wanted to tell us that the weather is clear".
「今日は晴れていると主張したいのだな」と
Time's up!
はい　終了　じゃあプリント回収して
Collect the papers!
Forest fires caused by arson
Both conclusions are logical.
どちらの推論も理にかなっている
Help us track down
counterfeit 10,000 yen bills
Arriving at the correct answer is pure luck.
どちらが正解かを言い当てるのは運としか言いようがない
23 members of
a criminal
organization
It's a dangerous time we live in.
最近物騒だな
@ 湮·Molly／小然·酸菜／喵儿·小冷／时末·竭力而为
KamiGami
Today is a real mess, but I get over it with a sigh
複雑に構えた今日が 息を呑んで澄ましてる
You get the idea, right?
身に覚えあるだろう 君はどうしたい
What do you wanna do?
You act as if nothing happened
何もなかったそぶりで  かばう痛みはもう
As if your heart didn't ache
It almost feels encouraging,
心強いくらいに 急かすんだ
the way you're rushing me
Hold it and let it overflow
掴んでこぼして 不完全な僕たちが
We're all imperfect
光って見えない 未来の自分を創れるなら
I can't see it well in the light,
but if we can change our future selves
目覚めるまま走れ 蜃気楼を追い越して
Wake up and run
Go and surpass the mirage
変わりたいまま走れ 自由な違和感で
Try to change and run
with the discomfort of freedom
届きそうな輝きと今を選んでいこう
We can reach that shining light
Follow it into the present
Don't hesitate to act
飛びたつ手を知らない
Deep or quick, just keep breathing
深い 浅い 呼吸を重ねて
Hyouka
Earth Sci. Prep. Room
Those Whom It May Concern
有印象的人
Hyouka
By the way, how was your uncle's... Sekitani Jun's funeral?
そう言えば
関谷純　叔父さんの葬式はどうなった
It came and went without any problems.
滞りなく　済みました
I see.
そうか
What?
何だ
I... just...
いえ　あの…
Oreki,
折木さん　もしよかったら　叔父にお線香をあげていただけませんか
would you be able to make him an offering of some incense?
Me?
俺がか
Yes!
はい　近々叔父のお墓参りに行こうと思っているんです
I was thinking of visiting his grave one of these days.
その　よかったら　ご一緒に
Um... Could you come along?
Okay.
わかった　行こう
Let's go.
I'll let you know when I've decided on a time, okay?
じゃあ　日は改めて連絡しますね
Okay.
You did such a great job solving my uncle's mystery and so many more.
叔父の件もそうでしたが
折木さんはいつも見事に謎を解きますよね
I honestly think it's amazing.
本当にすごいと思います
I don't mind if you call me lucky,
俺のことを運のいいやつだというのは構わないが
but please don't call me anything great.
大したやつだというのはやめてもらいたい
And you're so modest as well, Oreki.
控えめなんですね　折木さん
She just doesn't get it.
いや　もう　まったくわかってない
Chitanda, we can glean many pearls of wisdom from history.
千反田　昔の人はなかなかいいことを言っている
Such as?
何ですか
"Logic and cold compresses stick to everything."
「理屈とシップはどこにでもくっつく」
Oreki, I think you mean,
折木さん　それを言うなら理屈と膏薬はですよ
"Logic and plaster stick to everything."
Oh, I guess.
そうだったかな
Anyway, the point is that you can make up a theory to explain anything.
とにかく　理屈は何にでもくっつけられるってことだ
I get it.
わかりました
So let's just say that you were able to solve all these cases
折木さんがこれまで事件を解決してくれれたのは
not out of talent, but out of pure luck—
有能だからではなく　運がよかったからだとしましょう
Don't you think that being able to build a theory based on the facts
ですが　手掛かりを元に推理して　推論を導き出せるというのは
and reach a conclusion is a talent in itself?
それだけで一つの才能だと思いませんか
Are you saying I'm good at logic?
俺が推論の達人だと
You aren't?
違いますか
I'm not.
違う
I don't even understand how I reached those conclusions myself.
何で推論を導き出せたのか　俺自身わかってない
Isn't that just because you haven't really thought about it yet?
それは折木さんが自分を見つめ直したことがないからでしょう
Well, that's right...
まあ　その通りだが
If you're going to say that, Chitanda,
それなら　千反田　何か一つ情況を出してみろ
give me a scenario.
I'll prove it to you that it's not hard to just make up a theory to explain anything.
どんなことにでも　理屈をくっつけられると証明してやる
That sounds interesting!
面白そうですね
うん　ちょうどいい機会だ
This is an excellent opportunity.
I'll make you understand that you can't always depend on me.
俺が頼りにならないとわからせてやる
But what should I use?
それでは　何にしましょうか
Could those who shopped at the Koubundou by the station on October 31st
10月31日駅前の巧文堂で買い物をした心あたりある者は
至急職員室柴埼のところまで来なさい
please report to Shibazaki in the staff room immediately.
What was that about?
何だったんでしょう
Who knows?
さあ
Then let's use that announcement!
今の放送にしましょう
Please come up with a theory that explains the story behind it!
今の放送がどういう意味で行われたのか　推論を立ててください
Very well.
いいだろう　受けて立つ
Challenge accepted.
Here.
はい　どうぞ
Could those who shopped at the
Koubundou by the station on October 31st
please report to Shibazaki in the staff room immediately.
Your memory is as terrifying as ever.
相変わらず　凄まじい記憶力だな
That wasn't a compliment.
褒めてない
さて
Now then.
Could those who shopped at the
Koubundou by the station on October 31st
please report to Shibazaki in the staff room immediately.
"Could those who shopped at the Koubundou by the station on October 31st
10月31日駅前の巧文堂で買い物をした心あたりのある者は
please report to Shibazaki in the staff room immediately."
至急職員室柴崎のところまで来なさい
Firstly, let's confirm the key terms.
まずは　単語の確認だな
at the Koubundou
Are you familiar with the Koubundou?
巧文堂ってお前は知っているのか
Yes. It's a small stationery shop by the station.
はい　駅前にある小さな文房具屋さんです
お年寄りの夫婦で経営しているお店ですね
It's run by an elderly couple.
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
I've been there just once.
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
一度だけ行ったことがあります
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
What kind of a shop is it?
どんな店なんだ
It's just your average kind of shop.
普通のお店ですよ
Koubundou
It's close to North Elementary, so I think that's where most of their customers are from.
近くに北小学校がありますから
North Elementary School
小学生が使うものを揃えていたと思います
Koubundou
North Elementary School
So it's not the kind of shop a high schooler would normally visit?
Koubundou
North Elementary School
わざわざ　高校生が行くような店ではないってことか
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
Kamiyama station
Koubundou
North Elementary School
You could put it that way.
そうとも言えますね
Shibazaki
Is Shibazaki a teacher?
柴崎は教員か
Shibazaki is the vice principal.
柴崎先生は教頭先生ですよ
You're bad at remembering names, aren't you?
折木さん　人の名前を覚えるのは苦手でしたっけ
Drop it.
ほっとけ
"I don't do anything I don't have to.
「やらなくてもいいことならやらない　やらなければいけないことなら手短に」を
What I have to do, I do quickly."
That's supposed to be my motto,
不動の信条とする俺だが
but this is an important battle.
こいつは大事な勝負だ
I must put some effort in to win.
少しは気合を入れてかからねばなるまい
Firstly...
まず
Yes?
はい
We know that Shibazaki was calling for one or more students.
柴崎は生徒を呼び出そうとしていることがわかる
ええ　それは私にもわかります
Yes. Even I understand that.
Let's call this student, or students, "X".
その呼び出される生徒を仮にXとしておこう
Student X
This is so authentic!
なんだか　本格的ですね
Why don't you take a seat?
座ったらどうだ
Right.
はい
Student X
At this point we cannot know if Student X is one person or many.
その生徒Xは複数なのか単数なのかは　今の時点ではわからない
Student X
One or more
Shibazaki might be intending to provide educational guidance to Student X.
柴崎はXに対し　教育的指導を施そうとしているかもしれない
Or, to put it another way, he's got a bone to pick with them.
平たく言えば　叱り付けようとしているかもしれない
Why do you think so?
どうしてそう思うんですか
An inductive conclusion from the fact that no students...
生徒が職員室に呼び出されるのにろくなことがなかったという
are ever called out for being good kids.
帰納的推理によってだ
Oreki, are you taking this seriously?
折木さん　まじめにやってます
I haven't taken anything this seriously since I entered high school!
こんなにまじめになったのは入学以来はじめてだぞ
I might be the most serious I've been in my entire life!
ひょっとしたら人生で一番まじめかもしれない
Besides, if he called them to offer words of praise,
それに褒めるようなことなら
he would've named them directly in the announcement,
巧文堂で買い物をした心あたりのある者なんて
instead of just putting it as "those who shopped at the Koubundou".
良し悪しのわからない言い方をせずに　はっきり言えばいいんだ
Staff room
A student who was called for like that might not even respond out of fear.
あんな呼び出しじゃ　心あたりのあるやつは不安がって名乗り出ないぞ
The vice principal?
In the staff room?
What is it about?
The vice principal?
In the staff room?
What is it about?
The vice principal?
Did I stand out somehow?
A trap?
What did I do?
In the staff room?
What happened?
Why?
In the staff room?
What happened?
Why?
That's right.
それはそうかもしれません
What happened?
Staff room
Why?
What happened?
What is it about?
Did I stand out somehow?
Staff room
The vice principal?
In the staff room?
Why?
What happened?
But they don't know it's me...
What is it about?
Why would they call for me?
A trap?
No way!
Did I stand out somehow?
The vice principal?
In the staff room?
But they don't know it's me...
What did I do?
In the staff room?
But they don't know it's me...
Is it really about me?
Might be someone else.
Should I just go home?
Should I feign ignorance?
But they don't know it's me...
Staff room
Oh no!
What should I do?
I'm so stressed!
Are they mad at me?
Should I just go home?
Why would they call for me?
And this was an urgent summons indeed.
しかも　この呼び出しは急を要する
Because they said "immediately"?
「至急」とあるからね
No, they usually say that anyway. That's not it.
いや　呼び出しは大抵至急だ　そうじゃない
この放送はスタンダードなやり方から外れているから
This announcement wasn't done the standard way,
which tells us that it was made by someone who was panicking.
慌てていることがわかる
スタンダードなやり方
The standard way?
For example, if you wanted to call me to class 1-A, what would you say?
例えば　お前が俺に向かって一年A組に来るように放送するとしたら　どう言う
Let's see...
そうですね
I guess I'd say this:
多分こうです
"Oreki Houtarou from class 1-B, please report to Chitanda Eru in class 1-A."
一年B組折木奉太郎さん　一年A組教室千反田えるのところまで来てください
That's all? Think back to the other announcements you've heard!
それだけか
何か別の放送を思い出してみろ
俺ならこうする
I'd say it like this:
"Chitanda Eru from class 1-A, please report to Oreki Houtarou in class 1-B."
一年A組千反田える　一年B組教室折木奉太郎のところまで来なさい
"I repeat:
繰り返す
一年A組千反田える　一年B組教室折木奉太郎のところまで来なさい
Chitanda Eru from class 1-A, please report to Oreki Houtarou in class 1-B."
It's standard practice to repeat announcements like that, and not just at this school.
校内放送に限らず　普通こういうお知らせは二回繰り返す
なが　この放送では一回しか言わなかった
But they only said it once this time.
That means he was panicking.
それだけ　慌てているからと考えられる
And he certainly was in quite a panic.
それも並大抵の慌て方じゃない
それは
What do you mean?
They made this announcement after class, right?
なぜなら　この放送が放課後に行われたからだ
Oreki, please don't just skip all the steps in the middle!
折木さん　途中の説明を省かないでください
Skip... What a wonderful word...
省く
甘美な響きだ
Oreki!
お・れ・き・さん
Think about it!
だってそうだろう　翌朝に呼び出しをかけたほうが断然効率的だ
If it wasn't urgent, it'd be a lot more efficient to just make the announcement the next morning.
During class
Kamiyama High might have lots of clubs,
神山高校は確かに部活のほうが活発だが
After classes
but many people still go home right after classes end.
さっさと家に帰るやつだっているからな
If, in spite of that, he still made the announcement after class,
それでも　放課後に放送をかけたのは
that means whatever incident led to the announcement happened then.
呼び出す理由が放課後になってできたからだ
Night
To school
And whatever it was, it was so urgent that it couldn't wait until tomorrow morning.
そして　それが明日の朝を待てないほど急を要する理由だった
Shibazaki made his announcement hoping that X hadn't gone home yet.
柴崎はXが下校していない可能性に賭けて放送したってことだ
Oreki, doesn't that sound a bit fishy?
折木さん　なんだかきな臭い感じがしませんか
You're right.
そうだな
By the way, how can something sound like a fish?
ところで　きな臭いのきなって何でしょうね
How should I know?
知らん
If we take the next logical step,
次の推理柴崎が生徒Xに対してしようとしている話は公にはできない
whatever Shibazaki wants to talk about with Student X can't be made public at all.
We can't tell if this applies just for this moment, or the future as well.
それが現時点でなのか　永久になのかは　わからない
Is it because he didn't mention why Student X was being called for?
Xさんにどんな用件で呼び出すのか言わなかったからですか
That too, but there's something even more revealing.
それもあるが
もっとはっきりと現れている
I don't understand.
わかりません
Shibazaki is the vice principal, right?
柴崎は教頭なんだろう
Student discipline is normally up to the student instructor.
生徒を叱るのは生徒指導部の役割だ
That's right. Mr. Morishita calls for students quite often.
そうですね　森下先生がよく呼び出しをかけています
Where's the student instructor's room?
生徒指導室はどこにある
The second floor of the main building.
一般棟の二階にありますね
Student Instructor
And yet, Vice Principal Shibazaki called X to the staff room.
なのに　Xは教頭の柴崎から職員室に呼び出された
Student Instructor
Staff Room
This shows the gravity and importance of the matter.
これは事態が重大であることを示し
It needed to be contained within the administration.
また　管理職レベルで情報が伏せられていることを示している
Well, that's not necessarily false.
と言えなくもない
Um, Oreki...
あの…折木さん
What?
何だ
Based on your theory so far,
折木さんのここまでの推論を整理すると
I can only imagine that Student X was caught up in something shady.
Xさんが良からぬことに関わっているように思えるんですが
Yeah, that's pretty much it.
まあ　そういうことになるな
But then...
では
Student X...
Xは犯罪に関わっている
must have been connected to a crime.
Earth Sci. Prep. Room
霜降
气肃而凝
露成霜而降矣
Frostfall
Cold winds bind the dew,
and it descends as frost.
Hyouka
This is just a game with Chitanda.
これは千反田とのゲームだ
It doesn't have to be correct.
事実である必要はない
I wanted to prove that you can't make theories that fit reality so easily in the first place.
そもそも俺は　自分の推論がそう簡単に事実と一致しないと証明するはずだったろう
But what crime could it be?
それで　その犯罪というのは
Before that...
その前にもしこれまでの推論があたっているとすれば
If my theory so far is correct,
there's a good chance that there are policemen or other officials in the school right now.
今この学校には警察ないし それに準じる機関の人間が来ている可能性が高い
犯罪が起きたとすれば
If there was a crime, it must've happened on October 31st, as per the announcement.
ここにある十月三十一日だろう
Incident
Yet the announcement was only made today,
なのに　放送は今日
Today
ついさっき突発的に慌てて行われた
and it was made in a hurry as well.
incident
October 31st
announcement
Today
The reason for that might have been that the investigators had only just requested it.
これはその直前に捜査当局から依頼があったからだと考えられる
But they could have done so over the phone, right?
でも　それは電話で依頼されたのかもしれません
That's right, but the investigators would most likely be ready to take X into custody.
それはそうかもしれないが
必要とあらば　捜査当局はXの身柄を確保するだろう
そのためには　直接ここまで来ていた方がいい
They'd need to come here directly to do that.
Custody...
確保　Xさんは犯人側の人間として　呼び出されたのでしょうか
So X might have been summoned as a suspect in a criminal investigation?
Probably.
そうだろうな
Hey, this is just a game.
おい　こりゃゲームだぞ
Oh, right.
はい　そうでしたね
If X wasn't a suspect, Shibazaki wouldn't have been in such a panic,
犯人でなければ　柴崎は慌てず　余裕を持って放送できたはずだろう
and would have made a proper announcement.
I see.
なるほど
Then what crime could X have committed?
さて　ならばXは一体どんな犯罪を犯したのか
Can you think of anything
千反田　何か思いつかないか
Well...
そうですね
The first thing that comes to mind is shoplifting.
まずは万引きですね
They could also be chasing someone who had committed a crime somewhere else,
それから　まったく別の場所で罪を犯した方の特徴を追っていくうちに
but was seen by a witness buying something at the Koubundou.
その方なら　巧文堂で買い物をしてましたという証言に辿りついたとも考えられます
Witness
Shopping
Kamiyama Police Station
Witness
Shopping
Kamiyama Police Station
Witness
Shopping
Kamiyama Police Station
Witness
Shopping
Kamiyama Police Station
Witness
その場合　犯罪の内容はどんなものでもありえますね
In this case, it could conceivably have been any crime.
Theft
Assault
即答のわりには面白い
Sounds interesting for a quick idea, but...
が　万引きはともかく　証言の方はないだろう
I agree they could have been shoplifting, but I doubt they were seen by a witness.
Assault
Why?
どうしてですか
If the investigators had an eyewitness account of how the culprit looked,
もし捜査当局がXの外見や特徴を知っていたなら
they would have provided that information to Shibazaki,
柴崎にもそれは伝わってるはずだから
and he wouldn't have made a vague announcement like,
巧文堂で買い物した心当たりのある者なんて遠まわしな言い方はしないだろう
"those who shopped at the Koubundou".
I see.
なるほど
This incident happened at the Koubundou,
事件は巧文堂で発生し　Xのとった表向きの行動は買い物だったと考えるべきだ
at the Koubundou
and X had supposedly shopped there.
shopped
Was the announcement telling him to give himself up?
あの放送は自首しろという勧告だったのか
I have my doubts about that.
それにしてはどうもおかしい
Logic.
推論
The investigators didn't know how X looked.
捜査当局はXがどんな人間かを知らない
But they believed he might answer a summons such as this one.
しかし　放送かければやってくると考えている
Why?
なぜなんでしょう
If I had committed a crime and then heard that announcement...
俺が罪を犯したとして　あんな放送がかかれば
Could those who shopped at the Koubundou by the station on October 31st
10月31日駅前の巧文堂で買い物をした心当たりのあるものは
至急職員室柴崎のところまで来なさい
please report to Shibazaki in the staff room immediately.
Ten more seconds!
あと十秒
I've done it! The investigators still don't know my identity.
シメシメ　捜査当局はまだ俺が仕出かしたんだとは気付いてない
I might even get away with this.
これはひょっとするとうまく逃げ切れるかもしれない
Under what circumstances would they actually respond to an announcement like that?
あの放送を聴いて　素直に出頭するとすればどんな状況だ？
Maybe if he felt remorse for his crime?
罪を悔いていれば　とか？
No, then he'd just give himself up and it'd be over.
いや　それなら　自首して終わりだ
They wouldn't need an announcement in the first place.
今日の放送がかかることもない
What's wrong?
どうしたんですか
Let's just put the nature of X's crime aside for now.
Xの犯した罪の種類はひとまず置いておこう
But let's say X regretted what he did,
だが　Xはそのことを悔いている
and he apologized to the Koubundou.
そして　巧文堂に対して謝罪をした
In writing.
書面でだ
書面で？
In writing?
Chitanda, what's today's date?
千反田　今日は何月何日だ
It's November 1st.
十一月一日です
October 31st was only yesterday.
十月三十一日というのは昨日じゃないか
Why didn't Shibazaki just say,
なぜ柴崎は　「昨日駅前の巧文堂で」と言わなかったんだろう
"at the Koubundou by the station yesterday"?
Yesterday
Now that you mention it, that's quite strange.
言われてみれば　確かに不自然です
Why would you say "October 31st" instead of "yesterday"?
どういうときに昨日ではなく　十月三十一日と言うか
Because there's a paper in front of you that has "October 31st" written on it,
目の前に十月三十一日云々と書かれた原稿やメモがあって
and you're just reading off it.
それをそのまま読み上げたときだ
A letter or a notice?
原稿やメモですか
Yeah.
ああ
If the investigators knew that X had committed a crime,
なぜ捜査当局はXが犯罪に関わっていると知りながら
why wouldn't they also know his appearance?
その外見を知らないのか
And why would they think he'd respond to such a summons?
どうして呼び出せばXが出てくると考えたのか
In other words, why would they think that X regrets what he did?
言い換えれば　どうしてXが罪を悔いていると考えたのか
It's because X wrote an apology to the Koubundou.
Xが巧文堂に謝罪文を書いたからだ
Probably something like this:
大よそこんな感じだろう
To the Koubundou Management
"I'm really sorry.
いや　まったくすまなかった
To the Koubundou Management
On October 31st I visited your shop,
10月31日に買い物をした者だが
To the Koubundou Management
but when I was there I committed a crime.
私は不法行為を働いた
To the Koubundou Management
I'd like to compensate you for the damages,
損害を賠償するので　これこれのものを受け取ってくれ
so please accept this and this."
To the Koubundou Management
The Koubundou owners then gave the letter to the police.
巧文堂はその謝罪文を警察に持っていく
The police, or some other officials, came to Kamiyama High based on that letter.
警察　あるいは該当する調査当局は
その謝罪文を頼りに　神山高校に来る
This happened just earlier.
これがついさっき
When Shibazaki found out, he lost his cool,
それを読んだ柴崎は面食らい
and made the announcement in a panic while reading the letter.
文章に目を通しながら　おお慌てて校内放送をかけた
Wait!
待ってください　折木さんの考えでは
According to your theory, X wanted to apologize to the Koubundou,
Koubundou
Apology
Xさんは巧文堂に謝る気はあっても
Compensation
Accept
but I don't think he'd want to get the police involved.
Settled
Koubundou
Apology
Compensation
Accept
Settled
Koubundou
Apology
Compensation
Accept
Settled
Koubundou
Apology
Compensation
Accept
Settled
Koubundou
Apology
Compensation
Accept
Settled
Koubundou
Apology
Compensation
Accept
Settled
できれば　警察のご厄介になりたくないと考えているということですよね
Koubundou
Surrender
Arrest
Criminal record
Koubundou
Surrender
Arrest
Criminal record
Koubundou
Surrender
Arrest
Criminal record
Koubundou
Surrender
Arrest
Criminal record
Koubundou
Surrender
Arrest
Criminal record
Koubundou
Surrender
Arrest
Criminal record
I guess that's right.
まあ　そうだな
But if that was the case,
だとすれば　Xさんは謝罪文に自分が神山高校の生徒だと書いていないと思います
I don't think X would say in his apology that he was a Kamiyama High student.
So how did the police find his school?
警察はなぜここを特定できたのでしょうか
When the police asked the Koubundou owners if they had any idea who it might be,
巧文堂主人が警察に心当たりのある相手はいないかと聞かれたとき
they must've said it was probably a Kamiyama High student.
恐らく神山高校の生徒だと答えたんだろう
They would have been able to tell if X wore his uniform.
Xが制服を着ていれば分かる
確かに
That's true.
And if X had done something that stood out,
しかもXが何か目立つ行動をしていれば
it wouldn't be surprising for them to remember him.
記憶に残ってもおかしくない
Something that stood out?
目立つ行動ですか
That will be the key to deducing the crime X committed.
それこそがXの犯した罪が何かを推論する鍵になる
Koubundou
Xは目立つ行動をした
X stood out somehow, but that in itself wasn't a crime.
Koubundou
しかもそれ自体は犯罪ではない
X did something that was wrong.
Xは罪を犯した
Koubundou
But that crime wouldn't be found out unless he apologized.
しかもその犯罪は謝罪文がなければ　即座には見つからないものだった
Koubundou
X regretted his wrongdoing.
Xは罪を悔いた
X did something that demanded immediate action from the investigators.
Xの犯罪は捜査当局がすぐに絡んでくるほどのものだ
It must have be something more serious than shoplifting.
Xがしたのことは少なくとも万引き程度ではない
Like?
では
How would one stand out while shopping?
目立つ買い物
How would one break the law while shopping?
法を犯す買い物
The Koubundou is a stationery shop for elementary school students,
巧文堂は小学生向けの文房具屋らしいから
so I doubt they'd sell anything of value.
値のはるものがあるとは思えない
Wrongdoing
Shopping...
買い物
Wrongdoing
Shopping...
買い物
Good grief.
まったく
Good grief?
まったく？
X paid using a counterfeit 10,000 yen bill.
Xは偽造一万円札を使って買い物したんだ
Help us track down counterfeit 10,000 yen bills
で　でも　で　でもですよ
B...
But... But... But!
That can't be! It's unrealistic!
それはあまりにもありえません　現実的ではありません
It's not logical!
論理的ではありません
It's a failure!
破綻しています　カタストロフィです
A catastrophe!
U-Um...
ま　まあ
落ち着け
Calm down.
This was just a game.
これは　ゲームだったろ
す　すみません
Excuse me.
You don't have to take it so seriously.
まあ　あれだ　何も本気にしなくても
But that's not possible, Oreki!
いえ　でも　ありえません　折木さん
Why isn't it?
ありえないというのは何でだ
There are counterfeit 10,000 yen bills in circulation.
最近巷で使われているのは偽造の一万円札です
You knew that, and that's why you suggested X used one, right?
折木さんもそれを知っていたから
Xさんが偽造一万円札を使ったと言ったんですよね
ああ
Yeah.
But there's no way X could have gotten hold of one.
ですが　Xさんはそれを手に入れることができません
And even if he did, he could have exchanged it.
いえ　手に入ってしまっても　交換の機会はあったはずです
どういうことだ？
What do you mean?
How do you think he got hold of a counterfeit bill?
折木さんはXさんがどうやって偽造一万円札を手に入れたと思いますか
An ATM, I guess?
ATMじゃないか？
It's very rare for a counterfeit bill to fool banks and ATMs.
ATMや銀行を騙せるほどの偽札はそう簡単に出回りません
But if it was so well made, then X wouldn't notice either.
もしそこまでよくできているなら
Xさんが気付くのがおかしいです
じゃあ　つり銭
Then it might have been chan—
そうです
Yeah.
There's no way to receive a 10,000 yen bill as change.
一万円札はおつりにはなりません
記念硬貨を除けば　日本で一番価値のあるお金ですから
Apart from commemorative coins, it's the largest bill in Japan.
I get what you mean.
お前の言いたいことは分かった
So that means that the only possibility left is that X got it directly from someone.
つまり　Xが偽札を手にするルートは
後は人づてぐらいしかない
But even if, for example, X's dad got the bill during his business,
しかし　たとえばXの父親が自営業で
偽札を掴まされたとして　それをXが小遣いでもらっても
and then gave it to him as his allowance,
父親にこれは偽札だと言えたということだな
X could have told him it was a fake.
It's a fake
That's right.
そのとおりです
Yes. Even if he received it as pay for a part-time job,
もしアルバイトをして　手に入れたとしても
同じく交換の機会はあるはずです
he could've exchanged it the same way.
Could he have picked it up?
拾ったとか
That doesn't make sense either!
それもおかしいです
Well, I guess someone who finds a counterfeit bill and decides to use it to his advantage
まあ　拾った偽札を使って小遣い稼ぎするようなやつが
wouldn't be so eager to apologize.
そんなに早く謝罪文を出したりしないか
He must've used it, feeling guilty from the beginning.
Xは最初から罪悪感を感じつつ使ったんだろうな
Did he use a counterfeit bill?
偽札の入手先が分からなければ
Unless you know how he got the bill,
your theory isn't possible.
折木さんの推論も実現は不可能です
Ten thousand, huh?
一万円ね
Chitanda, do you like money?
千反田　お前はお金が好きか
Well, if I had to choose, I'd say I do.
そうですね　嫌いというよりは好きと言った方が本当だと思います
Would you feel bad throwing 10,000 yen away?
一万円を溝に捨てたら惜しいか
I think I would.
惜しいと思います
Unless it was dirty money somehow.
ただ　その一万円が不当なお金でなければです
自分の金であれば　一万円は間違いなく惜しい
Everyone values their own money.
X used it while feeling guilty, because it was his money.
Xが罪悪感を感じながらも　使ってしまった理由は
それが自分の金だったからだろう
He must've had the counterfeit bill presented to him as genuine money from someone else.
Xはやはり偽札を誰かから正当な金としてもらった
If it wasn't as payment or an allowance, it must've been a returned loan.
給料でも小遣いでもないとすれば　残るは一つ
He got back the money he lent, but he was disappointed to see it was fake.
貸した金を返してもらった場合だ
貸した一万円が返ってきたのに　それが偽ものではXもがっかりだ
Can you blame him for eventually deciding to present it to the elderly couple who ran that shop,
悪いと思いつつも爺さん婆さんがやっている店で使う気になっても
wracked with guilt as he was?
そんなに責められないんじゃないか
But surely he could just say, "This is fake! Give me another!"
それでも　Xさんは偽札だから　交換してくれと言えたはずです
Really?
そうか？　偽札はババ抜きのジョーカーだ
A counterfeit bill is like the joker in Old Maid.
No one wants to have it.
誰だって手にはしたくない
Yeah, this sounds pretty plausible.
そうだな　こんなことなら　十分ありそうな話じゃないか
"Hey, X, I got the money you lent me the other day."
お　X　この前借りた金返すぞ
"Ah, Y, thank you."
あ　Y先輩　ありがとうっす
一万円だったな　ほらよ
"Ten thousand, right? Here."
"Thanks..."
はいはい　まいど
He got it, and alas, it was a fake.
で　もらってびっくり　偽札だ
X must've lent money to Y, who was above him socially.
Xが金を貸したYは　Xより立場が上の人間なんだ
That's why he couldn't talk back even when Y gave him a counterfeit bill in return.
だから　Yが偽札で返してきても反論できなかった
At this point we can conclude X is a single person.
ここまでくれば　Xは単数だろう
The Koubundou is a small, cheap stationery shop,
巧文堂は安いものを売る文房具屋なら
so it would definitely stand out if two or three high schoolers
一万円札を使う高校生が二人三人とやってきたら　不自然だからな
showed up to pay with 10,000 yen bills.
She accepted it.
仕上げだな
Then what about Y? He must've gotten the counterfeit bill somewhere too.
では　YはYも偽札を手に入れていた
Maybe he got it back from Z, who was above him socially.
ひょっとしたら　目上のゼットから返された金かもしれない
If we group all the people after Y into "Y" as well,
Y以降の人間を一まとめにしてYと考えれば
who does that make Y?
Yは誰か
Some cruel ringleader, or the maker of the counterfeit bills himself.
良心的でない店の店長か　偽造元そのもの
The police are here because they think
警察が関係してきているのはXから出所を探れると予想しているからかもしれない
they might be able to get a lead on the source of the bills from X.
And that concludes my theory.
推論は以上だ
I put in the effort to talk about my theory for so long, and you repay me with silence?
せっかく長い話をしていたのに何も言わないのもちっとひどい
That's not fair.
巧文堂はあっちのほうか
So, the Koubundou's over there?
"Could those who shopped at the Koubundou by the station on October 31st
10月31日駅前の巧文堂で買い物をした心当たりのある者は
please report to Shibazaki in the staff room immediately."
至急職員室柴崎のところまで来なさい
思えば　遠くへ来たものです
We've come so far from just one sentence.
Yeah. The game's over.
そうだな　ゲーム終了だ
Oreki...
折木さん
なんだ
What?
I remember that you started this game to prove something, but what was it?
折木さんは何かを証明するためにこのゲームを始めた気がするんですが
Now that you mention... What was it?
そういえば　なんだったかな
What, indeed...
何でしたっけ
Oreki,
折木さん　それが何だったか　推理してみませんか
why don't you make a theory as to what it was?
Earth Sci. Prep. Room
Give me a break.
勘弁してくれ
Police Apprehend Forger of Counterfeit Bills
ほう　昨日のゲームのきっかけは確か瓢箪からコマ
Yesterday's game may have just been a game, but...
Looks like it got real.
Next time: Happy New Opening.
Happy New Opening
状況は非科学的に 感情のモンタージュ
誰が誰を呼んでる
振り向けば逃げてく視線（感じる）
気のせいじゃつれないよ アンテナは才能って言うでしょ
だって（だって） 知りたい（君は違うの？）
青春の温度差 今のうち正してあげるよ
明日解決するなら 今でもよくない？
君のミステリー解いてみたい
少年の秘密めいた背中探せ（今日も）
君はファンタジー 惹かれてゆくよ（ずるい）
膨らんだ好奇心 とりたくはないのに
気になるよ 興味深い どうして
次回　あきましておめでとう